# **UMANG MEHTA**

Location: Houston, TX <u>umangrmehta.github.io</u>

Email: <u>umangrmehta@gmail.com</u> <u>linkedin.com/in/umangrmehta</u>

Cell: +1 (812) 955-9507 github.com/umangrmehta

### **OBJECTIVE**

I aspire to work in the field of **Deep Learning**, **Machine Learning**, **Artificial Intelligence** and **Cognitive Science** & **Engineering** with applications involving **Speech Recognition**, **Voice Interaction**, and **Natural Language Processing**.

#### PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Graduated with a Masters Degree in **Data Science**, I am a **Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence or AI Researcher & Engineer** with 1.5 years of active development experience in **Natural Language Processing** and **Social Media Mining**. I also have 5 years of Professional experience as a **Software Developer** and **Team Mentor** with expertise in **Database Design**, **Java Programming**, and **Web Development**.

### **EDUCATION**

Master's Degree in Data Science

**MAY 2019** 

Luddy School of Informatics Computing and Engineering (SICE), Indiana University, Bloomington Major Courses: Advanced NLP, Machine Learning, Deep Learning Systems, Data Mining, Elements of AI, Algorithms Design and Analysis, Statistical Inference, Advanced Database Concepts, High-Performance Big Data Systems. GPA: 3.6

# Bachelor's Degree in Computer Engineering

**MAY 2013** 

*K J Somaiya College of Engineering (KJSCE), Mumbai University, India* Graduated with SECOND Class, aggregate 59.77% equivalent to GPA 3.21.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Languages:** Java (5 yrs), Scala (1 yr), Python (2 yrs), Javascript (5 yrs), C/C++, GraphQL, Gremlin,

R, MATLAB, Groovy (1 yr), PHP(3 yrs)

Database: RDBMS- MySQL(5 yrs), PostgreSQL, Oracle; NoSQL- MongoDB(1 yr), Apache Solr(2

yrs), Elasticsearch, Redis; Graph - Neo4J, Janus Graph, Dgraph

Web Design: HTML5-CSS3(4 yrs), JQuery(4 yrs), AngularJS(3 yrs), UnderscoreJS(3 yrs), AJAX(4

yrs), JSON(4 yrs), Bootstrap(4 yrs), Polymer

**Frameworks:** Spring Framework(3 yrs), Hibernate ORM(3 yrs), Play Framework(1 yr), Morphia,

Smack(XMPP), JSSC, Apache HTTP(3 yrs), PHP-MySQL(1 yr), Symfony Framework,

Doctrine ORM, NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, NetworkX, Django, Flask, ND4J

**Machine Learning:** TensorFlow(1 yr), Keras, Deeplearning4J, Scikit-Learn(1 yr)

NLP Toolkits: Rasa, NLTK, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, OpenNLP, Spark NLP, Polyglot, Gensim

Big Data: Hadoop, Spark

**Project Utility:** VCS - Git, SVN; Dependency - Maven, Gradle, Composer, NPM; SCRUM - Jira

Servers: Apache 2, Apache Tomcat 7-8, NodeJS, Netty, Openfire, Nginx, WildFly

**Deployment Tools:** Docker, Kubernetes, AWS Lambda, AWS EC2, AWS Sagemaker

**OS:** Ubuntu(Linux), Windows, macOS

Cloud: Amazon Web Services(AWS), Google Cloud Services(GCS)

**Certification:** Oracle Certified Professional JavaSE6 Programmer

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Hello Nesh Inc., Houston, TX

**JUNE 2019 - OCT 2019** 

Data Science Intern

- Extract actionable insights from public and private data and represent them into Knowledge Graph to grow the Brain of Nesh.
- Improve the natural language understanding of Nesh to enhance its social interaction skills.
- Incorporate data-driven models into Nesh AI engine.
- Implemented **Conversational AI** Assistant backend using **Rasa** framework in **Python** with a pipeline consisting of **Intent Classifier**, **Spacy**, **CRF Entity Extractor**, **POS Tagging** and **Constituent Parsing**.
- Trained and deployed **Deep Learning Neural Network** models with **Dense Neural Networks** and **LSTM** for Text Classification using **TensorFlow**, **Keras** and **SciKit-Learn** through **AWS Sagemaker** in **Python**.
- Built Question Answer System based on **BERT** in **Python** served using **Flask** and deployed on **AWS EC2**.
- Developed a Knowledge Graph using Dgraph as graph database and GraphQL as query language deployed on Linux using Docker through AWS EC2.
- Integrated a Knowledge Extraction pipeline with the Knowledge Graph with stages and components involving Web Scraping and HTML Parsing with BeautifulSoup; Named Entity Recognition(NER) with Spacy, Duckling and Conditional Random Fields; Topic Modeling with TextRazor and Gensim in Python deployed through AWS EC2, AWS DynamoDB and AWS S3.
- Programmed a Data Access Layer for Knowledge Graph in NodeJS and Javascript deployed through AWS Lambda.
- Conceptualized and developed PoC of Diagnostic and Predictive Analysis of Oil Well Failure with Maximum-Likelihood(MLE) and Maximum-A-Priori(MAP) estimations and Expectation-Maximization(EM) Algorithm with basic feature engineering using NumPy, SciPy, Pandas and SciKit-Learn in Python.
- Maintained code and development pipeline using **Git** on **Bitbucket**.
- Followed SCRUM Agile Development processes using Jira.
- **Technologies & Tools**: Python, Java, Rasa, TensorFlow, Keras, SciKit-Learn, BERT, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, TextRazor, Gensim, Dash by Plotly, NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, Flask, Dgraph, Docker, Kubernetes, Nginx, Git, AWS EC2, AWS S3, AWS RDS, AWS Lambda, AWS Sagemaker, AWS DynamoDB, Gremlin, JanusGraph, Linux, Javascript, NodeJS

# Kelley School of Business, Bloomington, IN

**JUNE 2018 - MAY 2019** 

Graduate Research Assistant under Prof. Matthew Josefy

- Worked under Prof. Matthew Josefy utilizing ML & NLP for research on Strategy & Entrepreneurship.
- Research and implement NLP methods to extract relevant information from SEC Filings.
- Develop or implement models using ML and NLP to analyze the business model and board leadership structure of companies.
- Built ML models using **NumPy**, **Pandas** and **SciKit-Learn** in **Python**.
- Implemented Semantic Extraction with NER using Stanford CoreNLP and Spacy in Java and Python.
- Integrated a download and parsing pipeline for SEC Filings using **BeautifulSoup** in **Python**.
- Deployed the projects on an on-premise **Windows** system.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Python, Java, NumPy, SciKit-Learn, Pandas, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, Git, TensorFlow, Keras, BeautifulSoup, Windows

# AriaData Inc.(Aridat), Bloomington, IN

**FEB 2018 - MAY 2019** 

Chief NLP Research Engineer (Unpaid Position)

- Build an analytics engine to determine the critical reception of an artists work based on chatter on social media.
- Leading and advising on the research and implementations of advanced NLP methods to improve the efficiency of the Sentiment Classifier and add new functionality to improvise the analytics provided to the artists.
- Developed a Data Preprocessing and Feature Engineering module using NLTK with steps involving POS Tagging, Stop Words Removal, Stemming and Lemmatization, Negation Handling, N-gram and

- Sentiment Scores using Afinn and TextBlob.
- Built Sentiment Classifier using and ensemble method of Naïve Bayes and Multiclass Logistic Regression to classify tweets from artists as +1, 0 and −1 and implemented metrics to analyze sentiment distribution over different demographics.
- Deployed the project on an on-premise **Linux** system.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Python, Java, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Stanford CoreNLP, NLTK, Afinn, TextBlob, MongoDB, Git, Matplotlib, Plotly, TensorFlow, Keras, Linux

# **Vitruvian Technologies Pvt. Ltd.(VTPL),** Mumbai, India Senior Developer & Team Mentor

**JUNE 2014 - JULY 2017** 

- Developed functionalities for web-based ERP and CRM systems in the domain of Real Estate.
- Collaborated in a team of 12 for project development including Object Oriented Programming using Spring in Java & Groovy and Reactive Programming using Play in Scala
- Handled Data Structure & Database Design in Java, Hibernate & MySQL
- Designed and developed Web Applications with HTML 5, CSS 3, Javascript, Jquery, AngularJS, UnderscoreJS, Spring MVC in Java & Laravel in PHP
- Built Full-Text Search functionalities with Apache Solr and ElasticSearch
- Developed a routing software to redirect users to different tenant clusters based on the user logging in through a central login page using **Java**.
- Deployed projects using AWS EC2, AWS S3, AWS RDS, AWS Route53, AWS Cloud CDN and Linux
- Used **Git** and **SVN** as version control systems for different projects
- Lead, trained and mentored a sub-team of 5 throughout the development of the projects
- Contributed to the Core Framework, proprietarily used by the firm for project development.
- Technologies & Tools: Java, Scala, Groovy, Spring Framework, Hibernate ORM, MySQL, Apache Solr, ElasticSearch, HTML 5, CSS 3, Javascript, AngularJS, UnderscoreJS, Bootstrap, AJAX, Jquery, PHP, Laravel Framework, Play Framework, Git, SVN, AWS EC2, AWS S3, AWS RDS, AWS Route53, AWS Cloud CDN, Linux

# Algonation, Mumbai, India

**JUNE 2013 - MAY 2014** 

Co-founder, Developer

- Developed websites, web portals and mobile apps using HTML 5, CSS 3, Bootstrap, Javascript, AJAX, Jquery, PHP and MySQL for small and medium scale enterprises.
- Built IM Chat Apps using Java, XMPP, Smack and Openfire on Android OS.
- Built server software for TCP Layer Protocols customized for cloud-based industrial requirements with Java, Netty, RabbitMQ and MySQL deployed on Linux using Google Cloud Services.
- Developed standalone and distributed software for some stages of manufacturing production lines using **Java** and **JavaFX** for **Windows**.
- Mentored and trained groups of 3-4 undergraduate interns for developing industry level projects.
- **Technologies & Tools**: Java, PHP, HTML 5, CSS 3, Bootstrap, Javascript, AJAX, Jquery, PHP, RabbitMQ, Netty, JavaFX, Openfire, Smack, XMPP, MySQL, Linux, Windows, Google Cloud Services

# **Research Innovation Incubation Design Laboratory (Riidl),** Mumbai, India Software Engineer Intern

**JUNE 2012 - MAY 2013** 

- Developed a web-based ERP application for educational institutes using **HTML**, **CSS**, **Bootstrap**, **Javascript**, **PHP**.
- Designed the data structures & schema and managed the database transactions using MySQL
- Built mobile App for the ERP using **Java Android SDK** for **Android** phones and **Java ME** for Java-based feature phones
- Deployed the ERP on a hosting service using cPanel.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Java, PHP, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Javascript, PHP, MySQL, Java ME, Android SDK, cPanel

## **ACADEMIC PROJECTS**

**Neural Conversation Model** — Seq2Seq Learning using LSTM/RNN

AUG 2018 - DEC 2018

- Built a Proof of Concept(PoC) for Sequence-to-Sequence (Seq2Seq) Learning process for a Neural Conversation Model using Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) and Recurrent Neural Networks (RNN) on Deeplearning4J (DL4J) library.
- Trained Model on Cornell Movie-Dialog Corpus.
- Experimented with High-Performance Computing (HPC) optimization options in DL4J.
- Experimented with Big Data System coupling with DL4J for Hadoop and Spark.
- Technologies & Tools: Java, DL4J, ND4J, Hadoop, Spark, Intel DAAL, Git, Linux

### **OpenIE** — Open-Domain Information Extraction

**MAY 2018 - PRESENT** 

- Worked for this research project under computational linguistics faculty at IU Prof. Damir Cavar for processing unstructured text and extract data, knowledge, entities, relations and mapping out event information.
- Enabling semantic search with concept abstraction and linking concepts to concepts in large knowledge graphs like YAGO, DBPedia and Microsoft Concept Graph.
- **Technologies & Tools**: Python, Java, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Stanford CoreNLP, Spacy, OpenNLP, NLTK, Neo4J, Django, Git, WildFly, Linux

**Speech Prosody and Pragmatics** — Detecting Prosody and Pragmatics of spoken language MAY 2018 - PRESENT

- Working under computational linguistics faculty at IU Prof. Damir Cavar for this research project focusing on prosody, intonation contour detection, focus and stress pattern analysis for the processing of semantic and pragmatic aspects of spoken language.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Java, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Pandas, Google Cloud Speech API, Git

**Image Orientation** — Classifier using Neural Network and Adaboost

**DEC 2017** 

- Developed a Multi-Layer Feed-Forward Neural Network and an AdaBoost classifier in collaboration with 2 people to identify the orientation of an image.
- Achieved accuracy of over 71% in Neural Network and over 67% in Adaboost on a test set of 1000 images trained on a corpus of over 36000 images.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Git, Linux

**Part of Speech** — Tagging using Hidden Markov Model

**NOV 2017** 

- Developed a program in collaboration with 2 people to identify parts of speech for English words in a sentence using Hidden Markov Model and Viterbi Algorithm.
- Achieved a word accuracy of over 95% and sentence accuracy of over 54% on a test set of 2000 sentences consisting of over 29000 words trained on a corpus of over 44000 sentences.
- Technologies & Tools: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Git, Linux

#### **Pichu** — Simplified Version of Chess

OCT 2017

- Collaborated in a group of 3 people to develop a program in Python using the Minimax Algorithm to recommend a chess move for a given board state.
- Used Object Oriented Programming in Python to maintain the game states.
- **Technologies & Tools:** Python, Git, Linux

### **LEADERSHIP**

### **Data Science Club at Indiana University**

FEB 2018 - PRESENT

President and Treasurer

- Perfected the foundational structure of the Club Leadership.
- Organized hackathon for analyzing the opioid crisis in collaboration with SPEA at Indiana University.
- Spearheaded the initiative of monthly Newsletter and a semester wise e-Magazine.

# **Students' Council,** K J Somaiya College of Engineering, Mumbai *Creative Head*

**JUNE 2011 - MAY 2012** 

- Organized Technical and Cultural Festivals in KJSCE as Creative Head of the Organizing Committee.
- Headed the Creative Team for Kshitij, the Annual College Magazine of KJSCE.

### EXTRA-CURRICULAR

- Won 2 consecutive Annual Fall Chili Cook-offs in 2017 and 2018 organized by SICE at Indiana University.
- Organized Bollywood Quiz as Event Head in Symphony, the Annual Cultural Festival of KJSCE in 2011.
- Volunteered in the Infra and Logistics Team for Technical and Cultural Festivals in KJSCE from 2009 to 2011.
- As a hobby writer, got my poetic verses published in Kshitij, the Annual College Magazine of KJSCE and articles on topics of technology published in the Technical Magazine of the Computer Society of India, KJSCE Chapter.